Oh, it's citrus, is it? It's 599, is it?
Everyone's talking about the MacBook
Neo, and you know, fair enough, it's
actually really cool. I'm reviewing for
that coming very soon. But, what about
this guy, the MacBook Air? This has also
had some love with an M5 chip. We've got
Wi-Fi 7, Bluetooth 6. They've doubled
the base storage to 512, although it is
100 quid more expensive than last year.
But, when you factor in the cost of the
storage upgrade, actually it's cheaper
than before if you were going to do
that. 16 gigs of RAM, 512 storage, an M5
chip for 1099. This is probably the
laptop that most of us are going to want
to buy.
To be fair, though, this new MacBook Neo
at 599, 499 for student teacher
discounts, which does, by the way, apply
to this as well, that is very tempting.
It's almost half the price of a MacBook
Air. The downsides, I mean, there's
actually quite a few. The main ones are
you're stuck with an iPhone chip, the
A18 Pro. Also, you have chunkier bezels,
a slightly smaller screen, you don't
have a backlight for the keyboard,
backlight backlight for the keyboard.
The ports are USB 3 and USB 2, and
there's no MagSafe. This has two
Thunderbolt 4, so you can output to much
higher resolution, high refresh
monitors, and two of them, only one on
the Neo, and you have MagSafe, so that's
not taking up one of the ports for
charging. You also get Wi-Fi 7 with
this, which is not that important,
although you do also need a Wi-Fi 7
router to take advantage of it, router
for my American friends. A higher
quality webcam. More importantly,
though, you get the force haptic, I was
going to say force sensitive, the proper
force feedback touchpad. On the Neo, it
is actually a traditional design where
like the corners go into the chassis a
little bit. Still feels good, but not as
nice as this. Also, the Air comes with
16 gigs of memory, 512 storage as
standard rather than 8 and 256. Also,
the storage is much faster. The M5 chip,
which we'll come to in a second, is
significantly more powerful. So, if
you're doing any kind of proper video
editing, any kind of gaming, rendering,
and of course, it'll make this a lot
more future-proof as well. You can
probably use this for the next 10 years,
honestly, and it'll be absolutely fine.
You also have Touch ID
in the power button here. You have to
pay an extra 100 quid on the Neo, so go
from 599 to 699 to get Touch ID. That
also doubles the storage and an extra
two hours of battery. Apple say you'll
get 16 hours on the Neo, you'll get 18
on the Air. 0.6-in larger screen because
we have the thinner bezels versus the
Neo. Also, you've got the larger 15.4-in
option if you do fancy a bigger screen.
I think that's it. There's probably
something else. There are a lot of
reasons to go for an Air over a Neo.
Whether it's worth paying an extra 500
quid, going from 599 to 1099, subject to
discounts and blah blah blah,
I'm not sure, but certainly this is a
much better all-round laptop.
Since Apple refreshed the MacBook Air,
and in fact, the entire Mac lineup with
their M series of chips, starting with
the M1 back in 2020, they've had a
problem, a really big problem.
They've been too bloody good, and so
anyone who bought an M1 Air, this one,
this lovely little copper color, the
design was updated with the M2 Air, so
the year after this, which got rid of
that sort of taper design, which I
actually really quite like. Also, it's
got these chunkier bezels. But, this is
still a fantastic laptop, very, very
usable. And I think one of the big
questions coming out of the MacBook Neo
is, should I spend 599 on that, or
should I get an M1 Air that might offer
similar performance in some ways? So,
the problem Apple have had is that their
laptops have been so good for so long,
there really just hasn't been much
reason to upgrade. So, here we are
again, 2026, new MacBook Air, and the
main reason, honestly, to consider
upgrading is the fact that you're
getting 16 gigs of memory, 512 storage
as standard now. Because in every
previous MacBook Air review, I've said,
"This is a great laptop, really good
value for money if you want, you know,
macOS, but you're going to have to spend
an extra 200, whether it's upgrading the
storage, upgrading the RAM." Now, I
would not spend another penny on this.
Just get the cheapest version. If you
need more storage, just buy an external
SSD. If you need more memory because you
think you're going to use it, then
you're probably best off going with a
MacBook Pro instead if you really needed
that higher performance. This base
entry-level MacBook Air M5 is exactly
the one you should buy, and don't spend
any more. Except for maybe buying a
power adapter because it doesn't come in
the box here in the UK and Europe and
some other places.
What hasn't been upgraded, again, is the
screen. Still 60-Hz IPS LCD, 500 nits of
brightness. It is a nice screen,
especially with True Tone, which you
don't have on the MacBook Neo. The color
accuracy is really nice. It's the best
one of these screens you can get. But,
for similar money on a Windows rival,
you'll get OLED, 120 Hz. This screen
needs updating next, and it's a little
bit frustrating that we've not had any
change this year. So, how much faster is
this new M5? Well, it's not just the
chip because the storage is also faster.
They've doubled the read and write
speeds of the SSD. I think that's
largely because they have just
discontinued that lower 256 gig
capacity. And it was the case before, if
you upgraded from 256 to 512, then you'd
get the faster speeds. So, that's mainly
because they've got rid of the 256. So,
faster storage, but the M5 chip. Bear in
mind, though, there are a couple
different versions of this new M5 Air.
The base model has an eight-core GPU,
but if you pay an extra 200, you not
only get double the storage, a terabyte,
but also it bumps the GPU up to 10
cores. So, naturally, that will have an
effect on the graphics performance as
well. But, the big headline upgrade with
the M5 is the AI performance, mostly
because each GPU core has its own neural
accelerator. This is the same case as
the M5 that we get in the MacBook Pro.
But, how will we know unless we put it
to the test? This is the Draw Things
app. I've got the M4, I've got the M5.
We've downloaded a fairly simple Queen
image one local image generation AI
model, 6-bit, the exact same prompt, and
we're going to see how much quicker the
M5 is.
Go.
And even just 30 seconds in, this is
estimating 31 minutes. This is
estimating 11 minutes. If this kind of
thing is part of your workflow, then
that is a heck of an upgrade.
But, I think realistically, most people
who are working with local large
language models and developing with AI
want, uh,
for lack of a better word, ton more
memory and a lot more performance, so
they'd probably go for a MacBook Pro
with the newly updated M5 Pro, M5 Max
chips. So, this extra performance is
obviously nice, future-proof, great, but
maybe not that useful to most people
buying a MacBook Air.
Well, let's put them to the test. M1
versus M4 versus M5, all updated to the
latest macOS Tahoe. And in terms of the
processor speeds, this is Geekbench 6,
it's between 60 and 75% faster on the
M4, and upwards of twice as fast in
terms of multi-core on the M5. But,
going from the M4 to the M5, it's a
modest 10% bump. However, jumping over
to the graphics test, this is where we
see some of the biggest gains, and that
is impressive. The M5 is still 34%
faster than last year's M4.
And it's a similar story when we run the
Metal version of the test, 38% faster
this year. But, it gets better, although
not straight away. This is Geekbench AI.
But, both the M4 and M5 are
significantly faster than the M1. And
while the M5's neural engine is a bit
faster, it's not groundbreaking. What is
groundbreaking is when we use the
graphics, the GPU, to run the same AI
test. And because we now have those
neural accelerators on each GPU core,
but look at those M5 numbers compared to
last year. 31, 99, 149%
faster. If you're running graphically
intensive programs that can take
advantage of AI acceleration, then the
M5 is significantly faster than even
last year. Although, even without AI,
just a raw graphics test, the M5 is
still a good 24% faster than last year.
To be fair, most of us aren't really
buying a MacBook for gaming, but they
have got a lot more capable, and we are
seeing more games now supported on Mac.
And in Cyberpunk at FSR 3 Plus with
medium settings, I'm getting a
borderline unplayable 28 FPS on the M1,
a solid 47 FPS on the M4, and a very
smooth 62 FPS on the M5. Even just from
last year, which no one realistically is
actually upgrading from, it's still a
good deal faster.
I also ran a quick Wi-Fi test because we
have gone from Wi-Fi 6 to 6E [music] to
7 now with the M5. Also, I had all these
at 100% when I started the test, and
we're down to 85% on the M1, 94% on the
M4, and also 94% on the M5. This is
still a very capable laptop, but it is
showing its age. And what I think will
be really interesting is how the MacBook
Neo, with its A18 Pro chip, compares to
these. So,
we'll have to come back to that [music]
in a different video. I think for a lot
of us, though, it's that question of,
"Ooh, is the Air going to be powerful
enough going forward? Should I pay quite
a bit more and get a Pro for better
long-term use?" Well, I can tell you,
with this M5 here, I am currently,
generating a image, the same one from
the previous test. Again, I have my 4K
Premiere Pro running here. We've also
got a YouTube video playing here, mostly
smoothly. I am, I think, finding the
upper limit of the Mac. Although, if we
stop the AI generation, now everything
is pretty much flawless. Yeah,
absolutely. So, there is an upper limit,
obviously. One of the downsides, one of
the compromises of the MacBook Air, is
that it doesn't have a fan, and I can
tell you now, actually, it's,
ooh, it's actually pretty hot
underneath. So, you are going to
experience throttling, depending on how
you use it, particularly for sustained
performance. Like, if you're playing
games for a long period of time, if
you're exporting video. Because it
doesn't have a fan to cool the chip
down, it's going to have to throttle
more quickly versus a MacBook Pro, which
of course does have a fan. So, yeah,
absolutely, you can slow this down if
you really throw some, you know, local
AI generation, 4K video, and a bunch of
Chrome tabs at the same time. But,
realistically, for most of us, this is
going to be more than powerful enough.
The M5 is an incredibly capable chip,
and you really should not spend more on
a MacBook Pro. Which brings me to kind
of the last bit of the video, really.
Who should spend the extra 500 pounds to
go from a new MacBook Air M5 to a
MacBook Pro M5, the base model? Well,
what are you getting? You're getting a
terabyte of storage as standard now.
Apple quietly updated the base storage
when they uh revealed the M5 Pro and M5
Max versions of the MacBook Pro. So,
you're getting double the storage.
You're getting a much nicer screen with
a 120 Hz ProMotion. It's mini-LED. It's
much brighter, up to 1,600 nits. And
it's more color accurate. You can spend
a little bit extra to get the
nano-texture option, which I have on
that MacBook Pro right there, which I
love. You're getting an extra
Thunderbolt 4 port, as well as an HDMI
2.1 and a full-size SD card reader. So,
much better connectivity. And of course,
the Pros do have a fan. So, as I say,
for potentially sustained performance,
that will help cool the chip, and you'll
get slightly better performance. And
crucially, you can just spec the Pros
ridiculously. You can spend up to 7 and
1/2 grand on an M5 Max 16-in 128 GB
memory 8 TB setup. The downside is
you're paying a lot more, at least 500
pounds more to go from the Air to the
base Pro. It's thicker and it's heavier.
That's basically the three downsides.
But, realistically, the biggest
competitor to the MacBook Air is the
MacBook Neo, its smaller, cheaper
brother. While this is a lot more
capable, for students, for your kids'
first MacBook, for your parents, maybe,
the MacBook Neo is going to be the one
you want to buy, because it's, as I say,
almost half the price of this. So, that
is the new M5 MacBook Air. What do you
think? Are you tempted to buy one? Are
you going to upgrade? Do you think
finally we've come far enough since the
incredible M1 that it's actually worth
buying a new Mac, or should we maybe
wait another year? Let me know what you
make of this in the comments. And if
you've got any questions, drop a comment
below. Just as a little thank you for
watching till the end of the video, can
I show you
this 2015
MacBook Air. The first MacBook Air was,
I think, 2008. So, this is far from the
first one. But, look at that. You've got
the glowing Apple logo on the back. This
is uh what have we got here? We've got a
1.6 GHz dual-core Intel Core i5,
>> [music]
>> 8 GB of memory, early 2015. And look at
those viewing angles, those chunky
bezels.
Still kind of like it, though. Look at
that tapered design.
>> [music]
>> Feels like this is only 2015, but it
feels like it should be in a museum.
versus MacBook Air M5 2026.
Let's put those side by side.
Thanks for watching.